all right
I had a couple of thoughts one thing I
thought about was a heatfulness or
diligence they're translated in different ways so
they're translated in different ways so
it is the quality that the Buddha says
is
where all skillful qualities converge
and is like
a way to not decline in the dhamma
so like
what is it
and
who does it apply to where does it start anybody else
and it applies to sort of one
so the heat fullness so can can somebody
without the Right View be hateful
no
in a common sense yes yeah whatever you
want to achieve you have to be hateful
so it actually applies even before yeah
in a sense that if you recognize that it
is your task to develop the Right View
and then you're heatful in regard to
that task it is the heatfulness that
will make you seek the Right View
and then obviously once you have the
right view that hatefulness will make
you develop it further so that's why
they would have singled it out as the as
the soul Factor because it would
he would actually pertain to somebody
from the moment of hearing about the
possibility of freedom from suffering to
the moment of understanding the fear of
suffering then fully developing it if
he's hateful he would he would find a
way
will that alone make him find a way
oh no of course not no
no that's why yeah you can be hateful
but um
if you don't come across the right
instruction if you don't attend to do it
rightly you won't
you won't
you won't get the right view well it
seems to me there's a difference some
something of a difference in what would
constitute heedfulness like you'd be
hateful in regard to what for somebody
without the Right View as opposed to
being hateful in regard to what so what
should a person without a Right View be
hateful about well
the heat full of the
Peril of not having the right view or
knowing that he's full of the fact that
you're not sought upon yeah
and like
take that seriously in that sense
so if a person is heedful about it
they you know they want like slack the
effort they want sort of fall into the
they want sort of fall into the
assumption that they know that which
they don't and so on because they would
constantly be Heathrow about the fact
that well am I free from the first three
Fighters do I see the four noble truths
am I my own guide do I need to defend My
Views am I beyond doubt all of that it's
like no no no no no no well then I'm not
there yet so I should remain hateful
so in other words heat will pretty much
stand for being
at that stage would stand actually at
any stage would stand for being honest
and authentic so a Sota Bana
Sacramento should also be heatful of the
fact that they still have work to do
so it would be the same principle
and it's very mindfulness you can't have
too much exactly exactly which I think
it's how it's sometimes translated as
well kind of synonymously
but yeah you can't you can't be too
hateful of the with the fact that you
know you don't have the right view or of
the fact that you you're not in other
hand yet and so on that that will keep
you uh practicing and directed towards the
uh practicing and directed towards the
practice so
so it seems to me that hatefulness also
refers somewhat not only to
specific things you do
but like the the extent to which you do
them not not only in the sense of how
intensely let's say you practice if you
I don't know you could do extremely
intense um trying to think about things and
um trying to think about things and
contemplate things and be as hard you
can do everything right for half a day
right if the rest of the day you're not
yeah it doesn't yeah that constitutes
just acting out of overly determined
mind we're sure if you know what you're
determining it can be beneficial
it can be beneficial
but in and of itself yeah it's not
heatfulness is on the level of the
mindfulness context recollecting your
situation what are you still subjected
to what are the can the non-ories and
lost their eyes can the non-reason anger
arise Canon there is a hindrances hinder
you all of that is reflected through on
a kind of hatefulness oh let me actually
be careful and check these things I
might be fine now but do I know for sure
I will remain fine in the future if if
circumstances change if things change
and so on and then
and then
keeping that in mind not
slackening in regard to us in the sense
that you know you can't
think I'll just do this for a certain
amount of time and then I'll take a
break it has to be basically done up to
the points up to the extent necessary
basically you can you can take a break
from the individual determinations of
I'll do this or I'll do that if it's too
much if it's too tight but there is
never a reason to take a break from
hatefulness in as much there's never a
reason to take a break from mindfulness
it's exactly the same can I take a break
now yeah yeah
is there a danger me taking a break now
so I can take a relative break in the
sense of I must forget that yeah there's
still work to be done so sure I need to
catch my breath you can't just keep
going in the same Pace but that
that needs to be understood that
heatfulness and mindfulness there is
never a reason or a justification to
take a break from
So to that extent you should never rest
because if your rest requires you to to ignore
if your rest requires you to to ignore
heatfulness and mindfulness means it's a
rest of essential distracting kind for
sure it's like um
it's like um
craving always leads to suffering so
there's never
a situation where
like relaxing in
unless you're completely free from it
yeah yeah then relaxing it would mean
inducing it so relaxing from hatefulness
and mindfulness so that uh like a
general sort of enduring memory of your
situation of your liabilities of all of
that that gives rise to identification
personality view craving everything else
that is already there underlying
Tendencies waiting for things to become
um suitable
for them to appear
so mindfulness that's where mindfulness
is the path to that deathlessness to
freedom from all of it
um
and it's it's it's it's kind of learning
how to be hateful and mindful without
needing to do it on account of your
determination and inspiration because
then when those things are gone your
heatenness and mindfulness is gone and
then you're back pretty much in the
perilous state of centrality and
liabilities yes because they are if they're fully
yes because they are if they're fully
understood
or at least initially understood
correctly you would get a hint that they
are truly effortless so you don't need
to rest from something that doesn't
require effort
then does that mindfulness that Heathen
has become effortless
by understanding it
understanding the nature of it and what
factor is the
allows it to be
effortless so you can understand it
there's another factor which
if you see you are automatically
careful if you develop you automatically well
if you develop you automatically well
like you're the only someone yeah I've
seen that the danger yeah attending to
it rightly yeah there are snakes in this
Forest yeah
knowledge of that makes you hateful yeah
so you're always remembering oh yeah
snakes oh yeah yeah if I get bitten by
sniper yeah so that's why like again
mindfulness established correctly uh
invested effort in in that sense like
you do need to initially make the effort
to recollect the context and protect the
context but yeah it gives rise to
knowledge to the recognition of certain
Universal principles
and exactly the dangers how to attend to
these things without losing the sight of
the danger and so on
and that is the you know like the the
famous practice of hanapanasate it's really not
practice of hanapanasate it's really not
a meditation practice it's a practice of
mindfulness which of course is a
meditation itself but not the way people
usually think
so the whole the whole idea of
um of these types of cultivation the
Sati patanas the anapanasatism is just
to
permeate all the aspects of your
experience with the same recollectedness
and same heatfulness
swindergarten body feeling states of
mind and thoughts
so in other words we're not trying to
save on my people sometimes have this
determination to practice meditation
they don't realize that Anna panasati
does not lead you to the absorptions and
experience of pleasantly Bliss of John
or whatever you perceive it to be it
actually leads you to being
incapable of becoming unmindful and
unhateful so to speak so yes if you have a
so to speak so yes if you have a
determination to practice meditation
practice the same hatefulness in
mindfulness sure on a kind of knowledge
of your breath
knowledge of your own sense of
self-breathing like this breathing like
that it doesn't matter knowledge of how
you feel while you breathe or while you
are kind of walking extending your limbs
eating dwelling in solitude basically
all of these things are there as your
situation as the basis the form the
feeling all of that and all you need to
do is learn how to
[Music] um um
see them
discern them be
Mindful and hateful in regard to them
without needing to do that
and without forgetting about them either
so that's the the the the tuning of the
strings so in regard to that there is this
so in regard to that there is this
let's say
subtle but kind of important distinction
that you need to learn how to see them
and discern them
then you need to be hateful in regard to
them so there is a point where you need
to kind of balance or stop trying to see
and discern that that balance would be
the beginning of correct heatfulness in
mindfulness that balance would be the
beginning of correct samadhi well you're
not overly concentrating and trying to
do it do it but at the same time you're
incapable of forgetting it yes so it's
effortless and that's
and that's
but that point where you say okay this
is where I just need to be heatful
like okay these are the snakes in this
Forest like you said now that's that is
dangerous I recognize that so now let me
just keep being hateful in regard to
that
but the Mind tends to keep wanting no no
I need to keep
you know what how can I be sure that
this is enough basically how can I
so my intents to overdo it yeah one
thing to keep it tighten it over tighten
it overdo it is oh dismiss the whole
thing I oh I'll run away from this
Forest but that's impossible either
so you realize well you you can't try to
run away which always resulted in you
returning back in the forest and getting
bitten by snakes because you
didn't discern them sufficiently enough
where the dangers are or exactly
becoming overly invested in Discerning
even stuff that you don't really need to
discern in that sense so knowing where
to stop
um knowing uh to recognize where that
kind of Middle Ground is that then if
you just dwell on investing protect it
can grow but not if you over tighten or
if you um if it's too loose either
because is it
the snake example you know walking
people who would know their snakes and
then be hitting the ground
constantly with a stick as you're
walking through the first and you just
but and then when something happens
like there's danger there's danger
somewhere you know there's insects
there's snakes there's this there's this
disease everywhere and then when
something pop
was that the bat was that the rabies was
that the disease of that I'm waiting for
so you just completely it's as if you
were already bitten you don't you've
gone too far too tight in your
you're careful but you've lost it you've
lost the context you lost the plot
completely and then if something does read it back
and then if something does read it back
to you you're done
so yeah you need to have that balance
and see okay there is no
there's nothing here you have a context
yeah there's nothing biting you so you
can then you can walk through the first
Barefoot to be able to basically kind of
and not forget draw a line for yourself
as to how far you will allow to act out
okay so there are a pile of leaves here
you know Hampton us might be hiding in
it so let me sweep it but that doesn't
mean now for the rest of my time in the
forest I will walk with the broom
everywhere now if it's looks good I avoid it if it
now if it's looks good I avoid it if it
doesn't it's all right but if you start
giving in
to know I'll sweep this and I'll sweep
it means you started acting out of fear
and concern and then you are losing
perspective which means now you're even
more exposed basically the more you act
out towards defending what you obviously
implicitly took is valuable and yours
well the why the the basis of the danger
that you're applicable to becomes
that's that that monk that was in the
going around the forest saying over the
pleasure with the joy with the Bliss and
they thought oh he must be remembering
his former wives or something so they
went and told the Buddha they would have
called him he says what do you refer to
when you talk about his pleasure in the
Bliss is it previous essential he's like
no quite the opposite he was a prince
having five cause of sense of pleasure
but constantly fearing for his life
whether his wives would kill him or his
relatives or his parents because he was
basically you know in line for the
throne or whatever so he was he had all
the gods and all the Palaces but he
could never have a moment of Peace
because he was just the more he was
defending himself and all the possible
permutations of the danger and the
attacks the more vulnerable he was
becoming internally he was being
attacked by himself that's already a
form of yet you're already being
attacked and then when he uh abandoned
the entire ownership identity craving
became another hunt he said now I live
in this forest with his factual dangers
Tigers elephants snakes yet I have no
slightest concern for my life and
whenever he remembers how he used to
live his home my God what a pleasure
this is now
like immeasurable safety amidst the
danger and it starts by not acting up
and it starts by not acting up
it starts by not really going out of
your way to to defend and address all
the possible suffering will land on you
so use common sense as those other suits
say like okay well if there's a clearly
a raging elephant or a group of Bandits
or something okay avoid it until you're
in other hand then you'll know what to
do or what not to do
but that doesn't mean you kept you're
not justified to be like whatever or
maybe this maybe there's always bacteria
here this is yeah it might be and
and
so like the highest safety
is
not needing any protection protection
yes but until you reach that point
it is that heatfulness that is kind of
your Refuge if you discern it correctly
like seeing how far the seeing the
danger in
um well in things that are impermanent
and things that are suffering in the
nature of things that you would usually
like to depend on then
the only thing that you can depend on is
your hearfulness basically well that
thing that you that you can't
wholesomely depend on that will lead you
to you know needing to depend on
anything not becoming negligent that's
it and and the more that you dwell on
see that's yeah if the one with the
with the Right View if you dwell on the
nature of impermanence nature of
suffering that it like naturally
the Mind turns towards seeing danger in
acting negligently in regard to that or
becoming or for heedless in regard to
that forgetting that
so it's like you don't need to do
anything more or extra or yeah just
within that you need to start finding
um subtler ways that you're still not
hateful enough yeah exactly because
obviously because if obviously
heatfulness is seen thoroughly developed
thoroughly you'll be an enhunt the fact
that you're not means okay so I'm
heatful overall but within this
heatfulness there are obviously things
that still resort to heedlessly yes
there are a lot of you know core Central
kind and so on but are still
obstacles that's why it's hard to do it
the thing is not to do like to have one
particular um
um
like moment of Insight or something but
to develop this completely to thoroughly
do this
it's not only
you have to keep at it basically it
doesn't matter
just yeah
I'm one way
of
I'm staying here for
um could be too
see where do I seek gratification and
see the danger in
in those places yeah yeah definitely
because that's why a mind would still be
seeking gratification in those places
because you haven't actually stopped and
thought about wait a minute but that is
dangerous that pertains to the same
principle that I'm trying to abandon
that is not for my good that's for my
arm that's for the harm of others so I
should better avoid it having considered
us it will be easier
so